<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter written by Mr. Paul Bayne, minister of Gods word, lately deceased. Effectually instructing, and earnestly prouoking to true repentance, loue, and new obedience. Very profitable for euery one that would proceede on in the constant course of a godly life, shewing the way vnto it, and seriously exciting vnto more perfection therein</title>
            <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113834</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849063</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849063</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14194</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06051)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14194)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 697:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter written by Mr. Paul Bayne, minister of Gods word, lately deceased. Effectually instructing, and earnestly prouoking to true repentance, loue, and new obedience. Very profitable for euery one that would proceede on in the constant course of a godly life, shewing the way vnto it, and seriously exciting vnto more perfection therein</title>
                  <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 90 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by F. K[ingston] for Nathan Newbery, and are to be sold at S. Peters in Cornhill, and in Popes head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A holy helper in Gods building.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14194:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14194:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER WRIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEN BY M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. PAVL BAYNE, Miniſter of Gods word, lately deceaſed.</p>
            <p>Effectually inſtructing, and earneſtly prouoking to true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, loue, and new obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>Very profitable for euery one that would proceede on in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant courſe of a godly life, ſhewing the way vnto it, and ſeriouſly exciting vnto more perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction therein.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 PET. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord is long ſuffering to vs-ward, not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEB. 6.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>—Let vs goe on to perfection.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. THES. 4.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For this is the will of God euen your ſanctification.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted by <hi>F.K.</hi> for <hi>Nathan. Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſold at S. <hi>Peters</hi> in Cornhill, and in Popes head Alley. 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14194:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14194:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull, Maſter <hi>William Halliday,</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman and Sheriffe of London, all happines.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, this ſmall, but holy trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen mee by him, vnto whom it was written, to ſend it forth more publikely into the world. And knowing what euill and iniurious enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement Orphans often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times receiue in the world, except they haue ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial friend to countenance them, I am bold to adreſſe
<pb facs="tcp:14194:3"/> my ſelfe vnto you with this Religious child of a godly learned (but deceaſed) father for ſhelter: and indeed vnto whom could I with more aſſured hope dedicate it for harbour, then to your ſelfe, vnder whoſe roofe I and mine are harbored? and therefore that ſo in ſom part I might manifeſt my loue and gratefulnes vnto you, I preſent this with my ſelfe alwaies ready to doe you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good ſeruice,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours humbly N. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14194:3"/>
            <head>A LETTER WRITTEN BY Maſter PAVL BAYNE late deceaſed; effectually inſtructing and prouoking to true repentance, loue and new obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aſter <hi>D.</hi> I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude your wife in you, both your loues to that Saint departed, and to my ſelf, doth bind me vnto you in all Chriſtian du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, eſpecially to exhort you to repentance, and prouoke you to loue, the neglect whereof,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14194:4"/> though hitherto it hath been ſomewhat excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet hereafter it might iuſtly bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in me; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will breake off ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, laboring to build you forward in the graces aboue named. Firſt to deale with you in repentance, then to helpe you forward in new obedience. The Lord preacheth repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ſtill to vs: If a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger knocking at our doores haue their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere returned, they are gone forthwith to them that ſent them; ſo if the plague and ſuch like
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14194:4"/> meſſengers which God ſendeth to vs, had that they came for, they would not ſtill ring the bel at our dores, and cal vpon vs. Neither doth God waite for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance onely from the wicked, but hee would haue his deareſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren meete him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning themſelues; if ye alſo repent not more and more (when you ſee the examples of Gods wrath) you ſhal alſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh). Firſt, to ſhew you what this is, ſo I ſhall ſtirre you vp to it more fruitfully. By repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance I meane nothing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14194:5"/> elſe, but<note n="b" place="margin">2. <hi>Co.</hi> 7.10</note> godly ſorrow for ſinne, wherein the ſoule humbleth it ſelfe before God, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth home to him. It is not a worldly ſorrow (like theirs in the 7.<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.14.</note> of Hoſea) which maketh vs whine, becauſe the world is hard, nor yet a hopeles griefe<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ge.</hi> 4.13.</note> in feare of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t like <hi>Cains:</hi> but a griefe for<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51, 3.4</note> ſinne as it diſpleaſeth God, whoſe loue through Chriſt, wee haue felt<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zac.</hi> 12.10</note> ſhed into our hearts,<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.22</note> whoſe mercies we ſee in that we are not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, yea,<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6</note> whoſe father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affection doth ſeeke
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14194:5"/> to recall vs home by lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing correction. Now in this ſorrow, the ſoule doth humble it ſelfe, for this is the nature of repentance, it wil make vs<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 36.31.</note> take ſhame to our ſelues, giuing glory to God, partly by ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable acknowledging thoſe waies wherein we haue<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.5.</note> moſt prouoked God, partly by<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 36.30.</note> iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelues as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to bee cut off, that we may finde grace in his eyes, and not bee condemned. And toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with grieuing and abaſing it ſelfe, the ſtray ſoule<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26.20.</note> commeth home
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14194:6"/> to God, purpoſing (through his ſtrength) to leaue the waies wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in it hath grieued him, and to cleaue to God in all his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Looke then if entring into your heart you finde, that as much hath beene amiſſe, ſo diſcerning<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.</note> Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and patience, yea his goodneſſe, in giuing you the cal of his word and corrections, you are grieued that you haue been ſo vnkinde, and vndutifull, to ſo kind and carefull a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; if you finde that where it is to his glory
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14194:6"/> you loue to confeſſe your vnfruitfulneſſe, &amp; to condemne your ſelf, and doe with true pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of heart ſtrike a new couenant with God to forbeare your owne waies, to walke more fruitfully before him, ſo far as his grace ſhall preſerue you from the one, and ſtrengthen you to the other, (for all our ſufficiencie is in him); if you find theſe things in any meaſure, then reioyce, for God hath giuen you<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 11.12</note> repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to eternall life. But if your hearts haue neglected this exerciſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14194:7"/> of a broken ſpirit, and that your conſciences tell you there hath been little or no griefe this way; then you muſt be entreated that whileſt it is called to day, that Gods grace doth ſtill inuite you, you would not harden your hearts, but prepare to meete him.<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.28.</note> Weepe not for me, weepe for your ſins, ſaith our Sauiour, and bleſſed are they that mourne in this kinde, the Lord carrieth a handkercheife to wipe away thoſe teares, he is neere to comfort theſe hearts; theſe Aprill
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14194:7"/> dewes bring May-flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers; ſuch as ſowe in teares ſhall<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.5.</note> reape in ioy. Is it not better for vs to take the rod into our owne hands, and beate our ſelues gently, then force the Lord to take vs into his hand, who is a conſuming fire: if the Lord do but ſee you are willing to caſt downe your ſelues, and to deale with your owne ſoules, he will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer your heads in the euill houre, and make loue to your ſoules, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his negligent chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhall taſte of his temporarie diſpleaſure.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14194:8"/> Delay not this: our foules in their ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings from God, are like two bones beſide their ioynt, the longer they go they proue the more painfull, if wee take them in time they are ſet more eaſily. We wil take Phyſick, purge, ſweat, to preuent the growing of diſeaſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs; ſhall we not bee wiſe for our ſoules; the vomit of the ſoule, is the griefe of repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, take it betime, driue not of till the Lord bee forced to viſit. Now if God giue you to deſire that your hearts were
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14194:8"/> broken in his ſight, but yet you finde that you cannot (partly for the hardneſſe in your harts, partly for outward di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions) do the thing you would, I will helpe you a little at this lift. There is an art in blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp euery grace in the ſpirit, and this with the reſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore you muſt<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 30 1 <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.40. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.5.</note> enter into your hearts, &amp; conſider your owne waies. Wee will keepe a reckoning what we run vpon the ſcore with men, but rare are they, that thinke how deepe they are in Gods
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14194:9"/> books, ſuch ill husbands wee are for our ſoules. Now wee muſt heere marke warily, whether wee haue not loſt ſome graces which wee haue had; I mean, haue them not ſo powerfully as we haue felt them. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee doe not giue place to ſloth, doing Gods ſeruice coldly &amp; ſleightly; whether wee haue not forgotten our couenant which wee haue made with God in Baptiſme, <hi>viZ.</hi> of dying to our owne thoughts, words, and deeds daily, and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in our whole
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14194:9"/> courſe to feele that not now we liue, but Chriſt in vs, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, his ſpirit teaching vs to doe euery thing as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in conſcience of his will, to his glory. Yea, you here muſt call to mind, the moſt<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 9 7.</note> grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinnes which you at any time haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked God with, wee muſt not bid adieu to the remembrance of our ſinnes paſt and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, but muſt euer beare them in memory, ſo far forth as may help vs with godly ſorrow, holy baſhfulneſſe, and lowlineſſe of minde.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14194:10"/> Deut. 9. Now then thus ſetting the matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, if you finde not your harts pricked with it, then you muſt (as the Prophet ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) take words to your ſelues,<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14 3.</note> and trouble your owne ſoules, as thus; What? ſhall I thinke of my ſins againſt God, &amp; not grieue nor bluſh at them? If I haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſhot my ſelfe, ſo that men may haue a ſaying to me, it doth cut mee at the heart, I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; if ſomthing croſſe but my corrupt nature ere while, I haue griefe at will; and ſhall I not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14194:10"/> grieue for offending my God? If I had broke day, and not kept touch with man, I could not looke him in the face, ſhall it not goe nigher me, that I haue kept my couenant no better with God? If my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant haue loytered his day ouer, and not done my worke, he bluſheth, and is afraid to come before mee: and ſhall not I change my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and be moued that I haue been ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable in the works of God? Thus as men in ſwoones, being cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed, come again, ſo ſhall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14194:11"/> your ſoules, while thus you beſtirre them, feele ſome warmth return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them. But if yet the heart will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, you muſt in the third place, ſeeing your barrenneſſe and inabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, turn you to Chriſt ſpeaking to him in this wiſe: Were it to grieue at earthly occaſions, or that my ſelfe were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed, heere my affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions would come to mee before I ſent for them; but for godly ſorrow, none of it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in our gardens, our fooliſh hearts loue not holy mourning,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14194:11"/> our hard hearts will not relent to thinke how we diſpleaſe thee, we know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is no ſtrength in vs to any thing is good, look to thee, thou art the Chriſt &amp;<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.31.</note> Lord; thou giueſt repentance to thy Iſrael, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinne; thou (Lord) doſt circumciſe the heart, thou hamme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 36.26.</note> and breakeſt by thy Spirit the ſtone of them, making them fleſhie &amp; tender.<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 5.21</note> Lord do thou turne vs, and we ſhall be turned: Thus while you turne your eies to Ieſus that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Spirit, he will bee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14194:12"/> preſent to quicken this grace in you. But what if yet your harts ſhould not ſo kindly melt with in you as you deſire, yet al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ſafe, for this is the ſmoke of repentance,<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.20.</note> which Chriſt will not leaue till it blaze forth, hee will not put forth a ſmoking weeke. This deſire and labouring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, is happines it ſelf; Bleſſed<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.6.</note> are they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſnes; yea, vſing this courſe to conſider of your wants, to chide after ſome ſort your own ſoules, and to look to Chriſt the giuer of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14194:12"/> repentance, the ſtone of your hearts, the hardnes wil come away by little &amp; litle, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in bodily wounds the approuedſt plaiſters muſt be often laid on, you muſt not thinke, that theſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual euils ſo long grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on vs, ſhould bee quite gone on the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. I doe beſeech you therefore, as euer you would taſte the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of God; as you would find eaſe in euill houres, when nothing but God can refreſh you; yea, as you loue to eſcape much worldly ſorrow, which tendeth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14194:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> but to death, ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint your ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time with this exerciſe of a broken heart;<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they that mourne, for they ſhall be comforted,</hi> and wee know much more earthly ſorrow then we ſhould, becauſe we will not trouble our owne ſoules a little, blowing vp that godly ſorrow which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at our hands.</p>
            <p>Now for the ſecond, of helping you forward in obedience, the ſum of the couenant twixt God and vs is this; he in Chriſt ſaith, he wil take vs for his<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.23.</note> people, wee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14194:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> promiſe to him, that we will haue him for our God. This therefore doth compriſe our duty to God, that we ſet him vp in our harts as God; which thing wee doe firſt, when we grow vp to know him, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him in all things. Secondly, when we make him our truſt. Thirdly, when we loue him aboue all. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when wee feare him. Fifthly, when we reioice in him. Sixthly, when our hearts are thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected to him, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him their ſong and praiſe. This is to haue
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14194:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> him for our God, when we know nothing, truſt in nothing, loue, feare, reioice in nothing, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our hearts are thankfull aboue all to him. To ſpeake a little to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerals: We cannot haue God our God, till wee come to know him in Chriſt: ignorance doth<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18</note> eſtrange vs from God, and knowledge doth acquaint vs with him. This <hi>Paul</hi> prayeth for in the behalf of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians, 1.10. that they might be filled with the knowledge of God, the ſpirits of their mind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing opened, to look to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14194:14"/> him. Euen as our image in the glaſſe doth looke to vs from whom it is reflected; ſo Gods Image in vs doth make the eie of our mindes view him, the author of it in vs. Now this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge conſidereth of God two waies, either ſimply apart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al other reſpect, and thus it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth a ſpirituall eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, in reſpect of his properties, or perſons into which this diuine ſelfe ſame nature is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, the Father, Sonne, and Spirit, al of them hauing the ſame ſpirituall nature, as if I
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14194:15"/> and you with ſom third man, might bee ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all to haue but one and the ſelfe ſame ſoule and body, being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct perſons. Or elſe it conſidereth God, as made manifeſt in our Nature, for Ieſus the Sonne, hauing one, and the ſame Nature with the Father, hath taken ſuch a ſoule &amp; body as we haue (ſinne excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) to fellowſhip of his perſon, and thus is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.23</note> 
               <hi>Emmanuel,</hi> God with vs, or God<note n="f" place="margin">3. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in our Nature, in which humane Nature God the Sonne ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14194:15"/> death for vs, in which likewiſe hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted his Diuine power, raiſing it vp, glorifying it in heauen; ſo that he who was dead in his humane Nature, is now aliue in it for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, hauing ſwallowed vp death into victorie. Thirdly, it conſidereth God manifeſted in Chriſt, as he is become our God by Couenant, in regard of ſuch things which his faithful mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies doe worke for vs. He in Chriſt is our Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifier, our Sanctifier, that helpes vs againſt the remnants of our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14194:16"/> corruption; our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer that deliuereth vs from all troubles; the God that careth for vs, giueth vs euery good gift, bleſſeth vs in our eſtates, feedeth vs, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs and all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued ones ſleep, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs from al euil, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vs by his power to ſaluation, is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and ender of all his good graces in vs. Now how ſhort are we in this point, wee are like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants in a manner new borne, they are kept by the louing Parent, from fire, water, are fed, laied to ſleepe,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14194:16"/> made readie, vnreadie; ſhifted in their ſcape, but they know not who doth all this for them. So doth our heauenly Father by vs in Chriſt, but (he knoweth) little vnderſtanding haue we of him: for though God be light it ſelfe, a Spirit which brightly ſeeth all things through heauen &amp; earth, to whoſe pure ſhine the Sun is darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yet the weakenes of our ſight is ſuch wee cannot look againſt it: as the Bat and Owle cannot indure to ſee the bright beames of the Sun in the firmament;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14194:17"/> you muſt therefore take notice of your ſpirituall blindneſſe, and come vnto him that ſelleth eyeſalue,<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reue.</hi> 3.18</note> that hath the ſpirit of illumination, which openeth the eies of the blind, and crie to him for mercie. Why if your eyes were ſore bloud-ſhot, &amp;c. your eies wherewith you ſee but one another, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures like your ſelfe, you would ſeeke out for them, and waſh with ſtrongſmarting waters, but you would reſtore them; wil you not ſeeke to your God in Chriſt for to reſtore that ſight
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14194:17"/> of your ſpirits where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you ſee him, and the things of your peace within the vale, euen in the heauens? nay, you muſt bee aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med you take know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no more of your God through the whole day. If our children when wee are by them, ſhould through rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and careleſneſſe not once caſt a looke to vs, as acknowledging our preſence, would we take it at their hands? might not euery one ſay, theſe children they are better fed then taught? they are thus
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14194:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> graceleſſe. Let vs apply it to our ſelues, who ſerue our God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther little better, and you muſt ſet vpon this ſuite with better hope, becauſe God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to vs, this is his couenant, wee<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.34</note> ſhall know him from the greateſt to the leaſt of vs: the eye looking on a thing beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth one with it in ſome man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. But leaſt I grow too tedious, I come to the ſecond, wee muſt truſt on him, hanging all our hopes on his mercie and truth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs. And theſe two
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14194:18"/> go together; men ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the better wee know them, the leſſer we truſt them, and that deſeruedly, but Pſal. 9.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.10.</note> ſuch as know God, ſhall truſt in him, and who ſo repoſeth al his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God, hee takes him in ſo doing for his God: as the Scripture in this reſpect ſaith, the couetous man is an ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later, taketh his money for God; becauſe hee putteth his truſt in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine riches, his wealth is a ſtrong tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in his thoughts: and hee that truſteth in the creature, with-draweth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14194:19"/> his heart from God (ſaith the Prophet) tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that our hearts are vnited to God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.3.</note> when the affiance of them is ſet on him. Now though we ſhould liue by faith<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20</note> on the Sonne of God, truſting vpon him for the giuing and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of all our good both temporall and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, leaning vpon him for defence, and deliuerance from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils ſpirituall, yea, and corporall,<note n="i" place="margin">1. <hi>Pe.</hi> 5.7.</note> caſting all our cares on him,<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3.</note> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no confidence in the fleſh, but reioycing in Chriſt Ieſus, though
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14194:19"/> this is our dutie, yet we are exceeding weake in faith, and full of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe: this will appeare by our want of feare at the thretnings of Gods word and by our care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe, which maketh vs looſly looke after his promiſes. Did wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue ſuch threatning, (if you liue after the fleſh you ſhall die),<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11.</note> wee would tremble when we fauour our ſelues in our owne wayes? the diuels beleeue and tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Againe, truſting ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilly in mans word or bond, we do ſeek them carefully, and are glad
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14194:20"/> when we haue got the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and as we ſay, wee write vpon them, to haue ſo much at ſuch a day, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſubſtantiall mans word or bond giuen vs. But Gods word that promiſeth all good things in this life, as wel as the life to come, his ſeales wee ſeeke not after them, wee are not glad of them, which is a ſigne of our great vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe in them. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by the reſting of our hearts in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, and our being diſquieted when we want them, is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that our hearts are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14194:20"/> vnbeleeuing; while wee haue meanes and good likelihoods of this or that, wee are well, let theſe faile, we are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: which ſheweth that wee reſt not on the word of God, which is as ſure in the want of all things, as in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, but leane on ſuch things as wee ſee and haue at hand. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a man had crut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vnder his armes, but leaned not at all to them as hee goeth, take them away, he walketh as before. So wee, did not we truſt and leane on the things ſeene, but
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14194:21"/> on God who is not ſeene, but by the eye of faith, wee ſhould goe as vpright, when al things to ſenſe ſpeake the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, to that wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, as when our fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is fed abundantly, hoping againſt hope. Thirdly, did we reſt on God, and truſt to him, (as who is all in all) we would ſeeke to him for his bleſſing, more then for meanes, which by his bleſſing doe this or that, whereas we labour not to make him ſure to vs, but to get the meanes, and then wee thinke all is well with
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14194:21"/> vs. Now when you find your vnbeleef, you muſt make it odious to your ſelfe by ſuch like conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations. Shall I ſeeke after the word of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſometime, to ſecure but a twentie ſhillings matter, and ſhall I not ſeeke after the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes of my God? ſhall I truſt to a man promiſing this or that, and ſhall I not truſt my God, who is truth it ſelfe, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lie? will not a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall man thinke much, if I take not his bare word? and ſhall I not truſt my Lords
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14194:22"/> word and ſeale &amp; oath (he hath ſworn to bleſſe vs with all bleſſings in Chriſt) vnleſſe he leaue me a pawne alſo? Then in the third place, when you finde your vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing heart trouble you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2.</note> you muſt looke to Chriſt, who is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour and finiſher of your faith, ſpeake to him. Thou haſt begun, thou muſt finiſh. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe my faith, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, helpe my vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe. The third dutie is, you muſt loue him, for loue we know ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man one, ſo it doth cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14194:22"/> vs to God. Wee muſt labour to ſay from our hearts, Lord, what haue wee in heauen but thee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25.</note> or in earth in compariſon of thee. Now though we think wee doe loue him, and doe ſo, yet it is weakly, and aboue all things we had need to mende in this behalfe. Trie your loue and then iudge of it. Thoſe you loue, doe you not loue to be preſent with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as you two one with another? if one of you be forth of towne, doe you not thinke long til you meet together? are
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:14194:23"/> but ſhould bee affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned toward euery ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; if ſhee ſhould not care how long ſhe were abſent from him, but thinke her ſelfe beſt while they were aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; if ſhee cared little how her louing huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band were offended, caſting that at her heele which hee taketh to heart, were not this ſhameleſſe behauiour in her? and ſhall not we be aſhamed to ſhew no leſſe want of loue to thee, to whom our ſouls are married in Chriſt? Then you muſt turne you to God, confeſſing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14194:23"/> that your hearts are full of harlotry and falſe-loue. You can loue your ſelues, you haue affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enough to the things of this world, the gifts of God, and that the meaneſt, more then the giuer, as harlottes to rings, gold, bracelets, more then the ſenders, and beſeeching him to purge your hearts of this, and fill you with his loue: for this is his promiſe, I will circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe your hearts, and make you loue mee with all your hearts. The fourth thing is the feare of God: Sanctifie
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14194:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Lord in your har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, make him your feare:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 8.13.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28.</note> feare to offend him, who when the body is killed can caſt the ſoule into hell fire. We ſhold reuerence his excellent Maieſtie, and dread to offend him, becauſe hee hath been gracious to vs, and hath power to doe with vs what euer he pleaſeth. And with good reaſon were there from whom wee hold our houſe and ſtocke, ſo that hee could turne vs out of all at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: would wee not walk very circumſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, fearing that which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14194:24"/> might alienate his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour from vs? Againe, if the Maieſty of a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man doth affect vs (as of the King) with reuerence; how much more ſhould wee be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Maieſty of the moſt high God? Now you muſt know your hearts are much void of this alſo. The thing ſpeaketh it ſelf. Do you not feele when in prayer you are to ſpeake to God, that there is no reuerence in your hearts beſeeming ſo high a Maieſtie? Do you not feele the want of dreade at his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14194:25"/> which ſo long haue been vpon vs, and ſtill houer about vs and what awe is in vs, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vs fearefull by ſin to diſpleaſe him? Alas, preſumption, ſecuritie, hardneſſe of hart, theſe weeds grow ſo hic, that wee can ſcarce diſcerne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruit aboue named. In the third place the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you muſt worke this want vpon your heart, as the former, ſaying: If I were in the preſence of ſome great perſonage, and ſhould carrie my ſelfe rudely, without due reſpect, would I not bluſh? ſhall I not
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14194:25"/> bee aſhamed I haue no more reuerence when I come before thee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.19.</note> O thou God of glory? ſo for want of dread ſhall the beaſts tremble whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lion roreth: yea ſhall the diuels tremble to thinke of thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? O ſhall I be ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and no whit moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? So for want of awe in regard of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods law: ſhall I dare as well to take a beare by the tooth, as to breake the Kings law, where eſpecially it threatneth life, limme, or liberty? and ſhall I not bee afraid to treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14194:26"/> againſt thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, the breach wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is puniſhable with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death. Is there none but thee that wee may make bold with ſhall I bee ſo fooliſh as to feare ſickneſſe, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, mens diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and not bee afraid of ſinne, and thy wrath which is<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. <hi>12.</hi> vlt.</note> a conſuming fire? what were this but with little childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bee ſcarred with a harmeleſſe bul begger, and to bee dreadleſſe of fire and water. In the laſt place, you muſt looke to God in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, how this affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14194:26"/> is peruerted in you, confeſſing to him that you can feare the face of men, things that are, or ſeeme hurtfull to your ſelues: you can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emean your ſelues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently toward ſuch as are great amongſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but toward him you finde great want; and goe pray him to worke it in your hearts, who hath couenanted to put his<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.40</note> feare in our harts, ſo that we ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from him. Fifthly, to haue God for your God, bindeth you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in him:<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.4.</note> Reioyce in the Lord, againe I
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14194:27"/> ſay reioyce.<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 9.23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.4.</note> Delight thy ſelfe in the Lord, and hee will giue thee thy hearts deſire? let not the rich man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in wealth, the ſtrong man in ſtrength, the wiſe man in wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but in this, that he knoweth mee, ſaith the Lord. For what wee make our chiefe ioy, that is our God, for the heart reſteth chiefly in that with which it is moſt delighted. Now what is more equall, then that we ſhould ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace our ſelues in him, with ioy vnſpeakeable and glorious, who hath
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14194:27"/> deliuered vs from death ſinne and Satan (who as Gods executioner hath power in ſin and death) in him who is a light and a ſhield, that is a fountaine of all good, and a defender of vs from all euill; one able to maintaine all the good ſpiritual and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall which we haue, and giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs whatſoeuer is wanting: but if wee marke our hearts, their ioy is much depraued, (ſo that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith not without cauſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.2.</note> our laughter is become madneſſe); for our harts are not cheary this way:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14194:28"/> tell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the precious benefits are giuen vs in Chriſt, pardon of ſinne, peace, the beginning of euerlaſting life through the work of grace, hope through Chriſt of the heauenly Kingdome; why they can heare this and be ſo farre from lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping within vs, that we can hardly diſcerne them any whit moued. Nay, if we marke them the better, we ſhall ſee, that when wee would hold them to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of ſuch things, till they haue broke looſe from vs, they are not in their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14194:28"/> kind, cannot bee light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; as if God were the dampe of our mirth, not the matter of our exulting gladnes. Now when you obſerue, that you cannot reioyce in the Lord, you muſt ſhame your ſoules, by laying before them their owne courſe in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters. If I ſee ſome toy &amp; heare ſome ieſt, I cannot containe my ſelfe; if I heare ſome goodneſſe, or meete with proſperus ſucceſſe in my worldlie affaires, I can bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant enough; if I be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the time with my
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14194:29"/> friends at their curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inuitements, it go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on merily, dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes I feele them not for the time. Fie, ſhall I haue laughter euen till I tickle at a feather at ſome merry conceit, at good newes of ſome earthly buſineſſe, and ſhal I not reioyce in the Goſpel of God in good newes from heauen tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſaluation of my ſoule? Againe, ſhall I laugh and bee cheary in being with my frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and ſhall I be all amort when I draw neere my God? Shall I be glad of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14194:29"/> acquaintance with a man, and not bee glad y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I know my God in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, which is life euerlaſting?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.17.1.</note> The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked they exult, in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſin &amp; Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their deſtruction, ſhall I bee without ioy in ſeruing my God, who giueth of his free grace to me life euerlaſting? O our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing is earthly, little ioy of the holy Ghoſt dwelleth with vs. We are like ſuch as are ſicke of light phrenſies, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill laugh at their ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow, at their own phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, but can ſee nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>to, nay, diſtaſte that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14194:30"/> which ſauoreth of right reaſon. As therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the former, ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this alſo we muſt fight the good fight of faith looking to him, who hath ſaid hee will make our hearts glad in his houſe, who hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to ſend his ſpirit to vs, that our ioy may bee full; praying him that in this regard hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Kingdome may come and that hee would re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctifie this affection in v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to make vs able to tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> comfort in that whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is matter of true reio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cing. Now for prayſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God, and thankfulne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:14194:30"/> to him, wee haue this commandement,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6.</note> in al things giue thanks, yea in euils;<note place="margin">Iohn <hi>1.</hi> Pſal. <hi>104.</hi> end.</note> ſhal we receiue good things from God, and not euill, the Lord hath giuen, the Lord hath taken, bleſſed bee his name. No wonder, for medicine is as good in due ſeaſon, as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfulleſt dainties. Now our inward and outward croſſes are by Gods graces made wholeſome phyſicke to purge out our corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and make vs parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the quiet fruit of righteouſneſſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. Yea, our hearts
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14194:31"/> ſhould be ſo thankfully affected, that like a fire it muſt breake forth and inflame others. My ſoule, my heart, al with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me praiſe the Lord, Pſal. 104, 35. My ſoule praiſe the Lord, praiſe yee the Lord. He doth ſtirre vp himſelfe, and prouoke others, as the Cocke that firſt clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping his wings about his bodie, rowſeth vp himſelf, and after crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing awaketh others. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon termes of thankfulneſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are a court-holy-water (as we ſay) which our God that
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14194:31"/> looketh at heart and raines doth not reſpect. And truly there is great cauſe, looke at benefits paſt (eaten bread muſt not be forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thanks muſt ſtill be greene); doth not the particular deliuerance, when ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fell on each hand of you, bind you ſtill to thankfulneſſe. If all things you enioy, you know the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall bleſſings, as tolerable health, good name and reputation, freedom from ſuite and ſeruice, ability rather to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e helpful then charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the domeſticall
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14194:32"/> peace, your liberties without feare of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, all of them in their place no ſmall matters. Will you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſpiritual bleſſings, that which you haue downe in hand is as great a work of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as the glorious ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e you looke for hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Is not the Lords worke more admirable in his firſt making, and quickning the infant in the wombe, then in fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it there, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it forth, and nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it vp to full ſtature? ſo his begetting vs who were dead, to bee aliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:14194:32"/> (though yet in the wombe of our mother the Church) is more then the bringing of vs to a perfect man in Chriſt Ieſus, when now we are new borne babes in him. And though it ſeeme ſtrange, yet it is onely in this reſpect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are like infants who liue, but know not in compariſon that they liue; ſo wee hauing in ſmall meaſure that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which teacheth vs to know the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on vs, know not how great that grace is, which is already ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vs. It is no ſmal thing
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14194:33"/> when wee were dead in ignorance, and the luſts of our ignorance to bee quickned with the life of God, in knowledge, righteouſneſſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, when wee were enemies to bee made friends, yea ſonnes and daughters. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doubteth not to reaſon from this (as the greater) to life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting (as the leſſer) Ro. 5.10. If God, when we were enemies, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled vs by his death, how much more wil he ſaue vs with perfect ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by his life, that is, by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14194:33"/> putting forth the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his Spirit, now hee liueth to die no more. Theſe then are great things: his acquitting you from the ſinne and death for Chriſt the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ties ſake; his ſending his Spirit into your heart, and giuing you part in the firſt reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Beſide theſe, you muſt remember what aduerſities he hath hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen you in, how he hath eaſed the yoke of your corruptions, which haue had more power in you, then now they haue; yea, what euils he hath put by you. Haue
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14194:34"/> you not been tempted in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his or that kind, it is becauſe God in mercie would not leade you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temptation. Yea this is in ſome reſpect more to bee acknowledged the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> victorie when you are tempted. For, not to bee tempted is more immediately from God and leſſe in mans pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, then to preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt temptations. For nothing doth ouercom vs without our will, but without our wills, God doth leade vs into tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; for he knoweth we would taſte little of theſe, if it were in our
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14194:34"/> power to bee our owne caruers. You muſt bee as thankful for ſuch ſins which God hath not let you know, as for thoſe which hee hath pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in you, hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them. Whither doe you thinke you are bound to praiſe God more, if hee reſtore you when you are ſicke; or if he keep you, ſo that you feele no ſickneſſe? Now if you weigh what things God hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for you, they are ſuch as neuer eye ſaw, neuer entred fully into the hart of mortal man. Compare the ſtate of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14194:35"/> Prince <hi>Henrie</hi> in his Queen Mothers womb with his condition at full age in all the glory of his Fathers Court, there is a broad diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which may fitly reſemble the diuerſitie of our preſent and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture condition. We are borne ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God, heyres ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant to the Kingdom of heauen: but while the Church doth heere trauell of vs, we are pent vp in darke cloyſters, &amp; annoied with much ſtincks of ſinne in ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelues and others, but hereafter our ſtate ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:14194:35"/> be altogether light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, happie and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. So that wee may well ſay to God, O how great is the good which thou haſt laid vp for them that feare thee! How great things doſt thou worke before the ſonnes of men, for ſuch as hope on thee? You ſee then how for things paſt, for things preſent, and things God hath in ſtore for vs, wee are bound to bee thankfull. Now if you aske what it is in which our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe ſtandeth. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere; firſt, in a heartie acknowledgement of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14194:36"/> Gods goodneſſe to vs in all things, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of our owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe, as who are leſſe then the leaſt of his mercies.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Compare Geneſ</hi> 32.10.33.5. 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 29.14 <hi>Moſes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> 18.8.</note> Secondly, we muſt tell of Gods kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that we may glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him before others; come, I will tell you (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) what God hath done for my ſoule. Thirdly, it doth make vs caſt about, what we may returne to God in way of thankfulneſſe, Pſal. 116. What ſhall I giue the Lord for all his benefits vnto mee. Fourthly, it will make vs accuſe our ſelues, if
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14194:36"/> we bee backward in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Thus we ſee when wee receiue any more ſpeciall kindneſſe from our frinds, firſt, our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affections doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it gladly. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we tell what ſuch an one hath done for vs. Thirdly, we will thinke how wee may requite him, or teſtifie our thankfulnes at the leaſt toward him. Laſtly, we challenge our ſelues (if time goe on, and no to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of our good will be returned) as to blame that forget ſo great cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie as was ſhewed to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14194:37"/> vs. Now then that you haue heard what it is to bee thankfull, what good reaſon wee haue; wee muſt lay our ſelues to this rule, and we ſhal find wee come as ſhort here, as in thoſe afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named. O wee are hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly vnthankfull! what good bleſſings do we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, not once caſting a look to the donour of them. When wee are kept in the night, our houſes from fire, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into, &amp;c, when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed with ſleepe, when kept al day in our out-going and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings, when fed, doe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14194:37"/> wee acknowledge our God heartily in theſe, yet it is hee that watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, or in vaine they keepe the Citie; it is he that rocketh vs aſleepe, and draweth the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the night about vs; he giueth ſleep to his beloued, Pſal. 137. It is hee that wardeth about vs all day, keeping vs in our waies, Pſal. 120. He openeth his hand, and like a great houſe-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per giueth vs our daily bread. If in earthlie things which wee ſee, &amp; taſt, we cannot praiſe him, what taking ſhall wee bee found in about
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14194:38"/> heauenly, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue your daily ſins forgiuen you in Chriſt; when you are kept from the ſin of your own hart, the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt examples of world<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly men, the ſpirituall wickedneſſes that fight againſt vs; when you go in ſpirituall peace from morning to night, which alone is a gift paſſing vnderſtanding,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.7.</note> doe you acknowledge God with affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him in theſe things? it is he that ſhifts vs out of the ſcapes of our corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs in the bloud of his Chriſt from the filth
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14194:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> of our ſinne; hee forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs euery day our treſpaſſes; it is his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.</note> in which as in a tower, we are kept ſafe againſt all our enemies vnto ſaluation. Hee is the God of peace, the Prince of peace in Chriſt, who ſtilleth the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> accuſing, and ſubdueth the rage and vſurpation of ſinne in vs: we are like infants, that haue much done about them, but knowe not who doth it, take no knowledge of them. Our God doth carry vs on in the armes of his tender mercy. But alas, little doe wee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14194:39"/> of him. In be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits receiued often,<note place="margin">I meane not meate and drinke, but many other which in the courſe of the day are giuen vs of God.</note> our ſpirits do not once looke vp to him, but as ſwine take the maſt, ſo doe wee our bleſſings: or if we do any thing in way of thankfulneſſe, how ouerly do we turne ouer this duty? our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons more bent another way, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to that we haue in hand, euen the thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful praiſing of our God: we ſerue him as our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſerue vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they come in to vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their play, and haue got ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of vs they wanted, away they goe without
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14194:39"/> looke or leg to vs; but if they know we will haue it, then they doe them in ſome faſhion, but ſo, as we may ſee their hart is in their game abroad more then their dutie: ſo for ſpeaking what our God hath done for vs, (thankfulnes will not ſlip ouer a benefit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued) when doe wee with delight tell of his kindnes? When doe we beat our heads, not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering our te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples to reſt till wee haue giuen our God ſome argument of our thankfulneſſe? Alas, we vſe our God, as if it greatly mattered not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14194:40"/> how he were dealt with. Now then take words to your ſelues, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your harts this grieuous ſinne. Say if a man doe bid mee to ſupper once a quarter, I thanke him then, when I meet him after, I thank him of my laſt being with him, I tell what kinde welcome, what good cheere hee made mee, bid him home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, check my ſelfe if I forget him. But if ſome greater matters be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on vs, how kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe wee take them, how doe we loue to tell of them, how doe wee
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14194:40"/> yeeld our ſelues vp to them to bee at their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to the vtmoſt of our abilities. Shall I thanke him that giueth me a ſupper in loue, and tell of his louing enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, bee aſhamed if I make no neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly requitall? and ſhall I not bee affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately thankfull to my God, who giueth me all my daily bread; yea, who feedeth my ſoule with himſelfe in Ieſus Chriſt (heere is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, my blood) that I might liue for euer? Shall I not tell of thoſe fined wines, thoſe fatte
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14194:41"/> things euen of my God, broken in his body and ſoule with ſorrowes, ſheadding his precious blood, wherewith my vnworthy ſoule hath beene fed and feaſted? Shall I for ſome ſmall kindneſſe tell a man I am his to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded? and ſhall I not reſigne my ſelfe to my God, who hath paid my debt, and purchaſed mee a new ſtocke, euen the hope of eternall life with his precious blood? ſhall I bluſh vpon ſome more vnthankfull part to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and not be aſhamed of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14194:41"/> vnthankfulneſſe toward God? What? ſhall I be worſe to my God, then an Oxe or an Horſe is to his owner? If I ſhould ſhew one exceeding great loue, &amp; he ſhould not at all regard mee, or returne mee ſome common countenance, could I endure it? Thus then turne your ſelues to God, I am become worſe to thee, then the whelpes that feede vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my boord are to me: they will open and fawne in their kinde on me, but my heart hath no power to bee thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to thee, to praiſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14194:42"/> thee. O thou who requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of me in all things to giue thee thankes: &amp; haſt promiſed to write thy commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in my heart, put into my heart a law of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, O thou quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit, quicken my ſoule this way: labour for thankful hearts: God asketh vs but this as a rent for all his bleſſings beſtowed on vs: I will deliuer thee, and thou ſhalt praiſe my name, Pſalm. 50.15. Wee will not forfait things to men for not payment of rent: let vs not giue God cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14194:42"/> and ſtraine vpon vs, and all wee haue, for not magnifying and praiſing him. Thus if my God helpe you to ſtirre vp your hearts to repentance, and to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render your hearts to him by eying him, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting on him, louing him, reioycing in him, by making him your feare, by prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him with ſpirit, word, and worke: then happy ſhall you bee. If new plagues breake forth, you ſhall haue comfort in the hotteſt: and if you la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſee how farre
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14194:43"/> your hearts are out of frame, in their confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, loue, feare, ioy, thankfulneſſe, in regard of the impenitent hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and impudencie that is in them; for they cannot bluſh for that God knoweth by them, though our eares will glow on our heads, if men know ought re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochfull by vs. If you labour to finde this out, and then in ſight of your miſery, looke to Gods promiſe, who hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to giue you a new hart, a tender hart, in which his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements ſhall bee writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14194:43"/> by the finger of his ſpirit, then you ſhall ſee this courſe will neither let you bee idle nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable; yea it ſhall returne you much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and true peace: in life and death wiſe men will take the ſowre with the ſweet, and the world is not gotten without paines taking; therfore if it ſeeme to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bitterneſſe, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire labour, you muſt not be diſmayed, I will promiſe you it is but brackiſh on the toppe, the deeper you go, you ſhall find it the ſweeter.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing friend, <hi>PAVL BAYNE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:14194:44"/>
            <head>ANOTHER LET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter written by Maſter <hi>Paul Bayne.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MY Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> friend if I had ſooner knowne of your heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, I would before this haue written vnto you. For the more argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments we haue of loue borne vs by Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the more teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies we haue of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour towards vs. It pleaſed God in Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber laſt, to change his hand toward you, and to touch you in your wife, whom now hee hath againe viſited, &amp; I hope all with both your
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14194:44"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts. Truly our God (through Chriſt Ieſus is ſo mercifull, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all things are ſanctified by him vnto our good, all affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions though for the preſent not ioyous, yet they bring vs afterward the quiet fruit of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. Theſe euils which here euer and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non are preſent with vs they are fitly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to wayward &amp; touchie gueſts, which while they ſtay, watch euery officer, but when they depart, they pay freely. So it is with theſe, they oftentimes diſquiet the frame of the whole
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:14194:45"/> ſoule, but when they go away they leaue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of grace, of faith, of patience, of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that the ſoule ſaith well, it is good I knew theſe things. But the preſent working of ſorrowes ſeemeth often farre otherwiſe: for in ſtead of encreaſing in faith, our faith ſeemeth to bee ſhaken and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened, rather then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; and in ſtead of breeding patience and holines, our ſoules doe diſcouer more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiencie, rebellion, more vnholineſſe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way. Now the ſoule
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:14194:45"/> thinketh when thus it is ſhaken in beleefe, how doe theſe croſſes confirme faith? and when ſuch euill dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in vs doth breake out, how (ſaith the ſoule to it ſelfe) doe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons beget the quiet fruit of righteouſneſſe? I wil anſwere you theſe queſtions familiarly: when faith is ſhaken by euils befalling vs, you aske how it is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med? I anſwere you by a double compariſon: When a linke burneth dimme, to helpe the light, we knocke it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beaten to any thing
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:14194:46"/> it ſeemeth almoſt to go forth; yet this beating it, doth cauſe it caſt light farre more cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Againe, how doth the ſhaking of a tree by ſtormy blaſts ſettle the root and the tree more firmely, though for a while it threaten the downefall? Conceiue of theſe, and you may vnderſtand, how faith though it ſeeme to bee caſt downe, yet tried by tentations it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to bee ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened. Now then if you aske, how they bring forth encreaſe of righteouſneſſe, ſeeing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14194:46"/> you ſee more vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe breake from you by occaſion of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then you haue obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in your ſelfe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore. When a veſſell of any liquor, hath mud and dregs ſetled in the bottome, it muſt bee ſtirred, that which ſeemed pure muſt bee made muddie before it can bee cleanſed: euen ſo his troubling of vs, veſſels full of vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is the way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God doth cleanſe vs. Now if God bee ſo tenderly preſent by vs, as it pleaſeth him ere-while to be, it falleth ſo
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:14194:47"/> out that much gold, many precious graces are diſcerned, which wee before could not diſcouer: and theſe are ſuch ſweete ſowers, ſo pleaſantly tempered, that the griefe is not ſo bitter, as the working of grace in vs is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull. But what way ſoeuer, calamities doe not ſo hurt vs, as ſcarre vs; vs who are lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God, and called home according to his purpoſe. Thus wiſhing your peace, and hoping y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all ſhall turn to good, the good of you both, I ceaſe to trouble you.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14194:47"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
